Okay tell, so today we start the new פרק perek, *Perek* of
ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed Amud Bet*. I just want to make one
or two very brief comments about what we did yesterday over שבת
*Shabbat*. Thanks to Michael Covitz from me and also one or two
others saying before that.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had to end with some interesting practical הלכות
halachos. *Halachot* of how relating to דאווענינג davening *Davening*. Something we discussed
on Friday which I'm not sure I said correctly, so I wanted
to just correct it for the record, which is if somebody misses
הבדלה *Havdalah* in the חונן הדעת *Chonen Hada'at*, when actually שומע תפילה
Tefillah *Shomea Tefillah* is often an opportunity to make up missed things
if you like missed טל ומטר לברכה *Tal Umatar Livracha* and so
on. And although there is opinion that you can make up הבדלה
*Havdalah* in שומע תפילה Tefillah *Shomea Tefillah*, we rule that you cannot,
and it was actually absent from the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that possibility,
because we don't do things in שומע תפילה Tefilah *Shomea Tefillah* that
are not בקשות *Bakashot*. So the same way we don't say משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם *Mashiv Haruach Umorid Hageshem* if we miss it in
שמונה עשרה shmone esre. *Shmoneh Esrei*, we don't say הבדלה *Havdalah* in
שומע תפילה tefilah. *Shomea Tefillah*. So if you miss הבדלה *Havdalah* in
חונן הדעת *Chonen Hada'at*, then you actually just skip it all together
and you do it על הכוס *Al Hakos*. Another important הלכה halacha.
*Halacha* which we didn't discuss, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed if you
miss like יעלה ויבא *Ya'aleh Veyavo* before you finish שמונה עשרה shmone
esre, *Shmoneh Esrei* going back to רצה *Retzei*. Let's say you miss
something like משיב הרוח *Mashiv Haruach*, excuse me, טל ומטר לברכה *Tal
Umatar Livracha* and you are past שומע תפילה tefillah *Shomea Tefillah*. What
do you do then? So there's two opinions. Some say you go
back to שומע תפילה Tefillah *Shomea Tefillah*. But we actually rule no,
that if you still haven't finished שמונה עשרה shmone esre *Shmoneh Esrei*,
you go back, but you go back to the place it should
have been said. So you would go back to ברכת השנים *Birkat
Hashanim*. So the same way if you miss יעלה ויבא *Ya'aleh Veyavo*
you go back to רצה *Retzei*, if you miss something like טל
ומטר לברכה *Tal Umatar Livracha* you go back to and you passed
שומע תפילה tefilla *Shomea Tefillah* you go back to the place where
you could have where you should have said it originally. One other
point about it, there's a couple of important הלכות halakhot *Halachot* that
we said in the דף *Daf* yesterday, but I did just want
to make mention of the interesting factor around מוסף *Musaf*, that there
were opinions that you only are obligated in מוסף *Musaf* if there
is a ציבור tzibur *Tzibur* or that if there's a ציבור *Tzibur*
you're obligated as a יחיד yachid *Yachid*, but if there's a ציבור
*Tzibur* you do not have to say it, you fulfill your obligation
through the ציבור *Tzibur*. And that is clear that the reason מוסף
*Musaf* is different is because מוסף *Musaf*, while we've discussed all along
the tension between that sense of personal prayer and the fixed sort
of obligatory nature of prayer and if you would, prayer standing for
אבות *Avot* versus prayer for the קרבנות korbanot. *Korbanot*, מוסף *Musaf* is
all about the קרבנות korbanot *Korbanot*. And the קרבנות korbanos *Korbanot* meaning
the קרבן korban ציבור *Korban Tzibur*, the communal קרבן korban *Korban*. So
therefore for example there's no concept of a תפילת נדבה *Tefillat Nedavah*
by מוסף *Musaf* because it's about the sort of personal prayer, excuse
me, not about the personal prayer. And similarly there are opinions that
there's no obligation of מוסף *Musaf* or no need to say מוסף
*Musaf* unless there is a מניין *Minyan*, because it is only has
that aspect of communal prayer, of communal קרבן korban *Korban*, not of
personal. Now we don't rule that way, we rule that even if
you're ביחיד *Beyachid* and there's no מניין *Minyan* you still do מוסף
*Musaf*, but that doesn't necessarily mean you go against this basic core
idea that מוסף *Musaf* is about קרבן korban *Korban* and not about
personal prayer.
Though what would that mean that according to the דעה *Deah* that
suggests that you're not obligated if there is a ציבור *Tzibur*? You
have to be in the building? You have to be in the
city?
Yeah, that's a good question. Right. Precisely, exactly. That presumably means within
one's community, but exactly how one defines the parameters, the city, right
right, there's yeah, those parameters are not clearly defined because we don't
rule that way halachically, we don't actually have to define that, but
that was never made clear. And the last thing I will say
was the interesting issue in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which is a
theme that I've mentioned to you before about praying the רבנן rabbanan
*Rabbanan* who prayed in their even though there were thirteen synagogues they
only prayed in their בית מדרש *Beit Midrash*. And that also goes
to this issue about the sort of tension between the study and
בית מדרש *Beit Midrash* versus תפילה tefilla. *Tefillah* and not only a
general question of תלמוד תורה Torah, *Talmud Torah* versus תפילה tefilla. *Tefillah*
and how do we make those choices, but also between sort of
the rabbinic world which was the בית מדרש *Beit Midrash* and the
world of the בתי כנסיות *Batei Kneisiyot* which was not really sortณ์
controlled by the רבנים *Rabbanim*, it was a different type of leadership
of that world, and some of that was brought out in that
discussion or alluded to in that discussion yesterday. Now we begin a
new פרק *Perek* which moves us beyond the issue of the text
of the דאווענינג davening. *Davening* and the time and the text and
so on which had in it questions about כוונה kavana. *Kavanah* and
interesting issues we discussed about the position of לא תעש תפילתך קבע
*Lo Ta'as Tefillatcha Keva* and what do you do in order to
make it personal, to a direct discussion of the issues of the
mindset that one has and one brings to one's דאווענינג davening *Davening*.
So let's take a look now, bottom of ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed
Amud Bet*. אין עומדין להתפלל *Ein Omdin Lehitpallel*, one does not stand
to דאווען daven *Daven*, אלא מתוך כובד ראש Mitoch Koved Rosh, *Ella
Mitoch Koved Rosh*, only from a sense of literally weightiness of head,
seriousness. חסידים הראשונים *Chassidim Harishonim*, the original חסידים *Chassidim*, righteous people, היו
שוהים שעה sha'ah אחת ומתפללים *Hayu Shohin Sha'ah Achat Umitpallelim*, which spent
a full hour. Now again, שעה *Sha'ah* could just mean a period
of time. The גמרא's Gemara going to take it literally to mean
an hour, but they'd spend a שעה period of time, one hour,
ומתפללין umitpalelin and then they would only stand to דאוון, daven, only
after sitting quietly and sort of and getting their mind prepared for
a full hour. כדי שיכוונו לבם לאביהם שבשמים kdei sheyachavnu libam l'avihem
shebashamayim so that they should have the proper intent to their father
in heaven when they stand up to דאוון. daven. אפילו המלך afilu
hamelech now that since tells you sort of the mindset you have
to enter into דאוונינג, davening, we're now going to tell you a
related topic a related point about when you're in דאוונינג davening itself,
that sense of standing before God. אפילו המלך שואל בשלומו לא ישיבנו
afilu hamelech shoel bishlomo lo yishivenu that this is in direct contrast
to what we learned when we did שמע Shema that if somebody
welcomes you even a friend there are various times in שמע Shema
that you interrupt to respond. Here even if the king welcomes you
and greets you in the middle of שמע Shema do not respond
to the king. ואפילו נחש כרוך על עקבו v'afilu nachash karuch al
akevo even if a snake is wrapped around your ankle לא יפסיק
lo yafsik do not interrupt the תפילה tefilla here you are not
just
saying שמע Shema but you are standing before God and you do
not interrupt under any circumstances. And we will see how far the
גמרא Gemara takes this whether it's meant even literally include cases of
when one is in danger. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara מנא
הני מילי minani milei where do we know this from that you
only stand to דאוון daven from a sense of seriousness of purpose
and of focus. אמר רבי אלעזר דאמר קרא amar Rabbi Elazar d'amar
kra the פסוק pasuk says והיא מרת נפש v'hi marat nafesh by
חנה Chana and we'll get very soon to חנה Chana as the
paradigm for many laws of תפילה tefilla. so she was of bitter
soul so you see that that is somehow taken as a as
a paradigm that you're supposed to be of now of bitter soul
which is interesting but maybe you know just very you know you
know very again it's interesting to jump from מרת נפש marat nafesh
to seriousness but let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it.
ממאי mimai how do we know חנה Chana is the is the
example. דילמא חנה שאני דהוה מרירא ליבא טפי dilma Chana shana dehavat
mirira liba tufa
maybe חנה Chana was different that she did have she was very
bitter of soul she was very you know sad and upset because
she did not was not able to have children that doesn't necessarily
mean that that's to serve as a model for the rest of
us. אלא אמר רבי יוסי בר רבי חנינא מהכא ella amar Rabbi
Yosef bar Rabbi Chanina mehakka from here. ואני ברוב חסדך אבוא ביתך
va'ani berov chasdecha avo veitecha and I with your great kindness I
God will come into your house. אשתחוה אל היכל קדשך eshtachaveh el
heichal kodshecha bow down into your holy palace. ביראתך beyiratecha
with fear of you. So one enters into prayer אשתחוה eshtachaveh presumably
not only into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but enters into the
prayer with a sense of fear and awe of God. That's closer
by the way than the idea of bitterness of soul. So the
גמרא Gemara says ממאי mimai how do we know that that is
for all of us. דילמא דוד שאני דהוה מצער נפשיה ברחמי טפי
dilma David shana dehavat metza'ar nafshei berachamei tufa maybe that's just דוד.
David. דוד David was different that he would really anguish himself you
know when he came in his prayer so that was the greatness
of דוד David but that does not necessarily set a standard for
all of us. אלא אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי מהכא ella amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mehakka from the following verse. השתחוו לה' בהדרת
קדש hishtachavu l'Hashem behadrat kodesh so now it is not just דוד
David sort of reporting in the first person it is a call
to others bow down to God in the glory in the holy
glory. אל תקרי בהדרת al tikrei behadrat don't read in the glory
אלא בחרדת ella becherdat in the חרדה charada
in the trembling and the fear and the fear and this is
a call to others. So the גמרא Gemara says ממאי mimai how
do we know that that's the case. דילמא לעולם אימא לך הדרת
ממש dilma leolam eima lach hadrat mamash who says that I should
buy your little דרשה drasha of הדרת hadrat and חרדת? cherdat? That
you know why does that really prove this general principle. כי הא
דרב יהודה הוה מציין נפשיה והדר מצלי ki hadrei d'Rav Yehuda hava
metzayein nafshei vehadar matzlei like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda he would actually
make himself dress up nicely and then דאוון daven so there's an
idea of sort of you're standing in front of God and it's
a certain sense of you know appearing properly of glory not of
fear and of trembling.
He certainly is in terms of הלכה. Halacha?
What? Right exactly you're supposed to dress nicely or עמדה לפני המלך
omda lifnei hamelech but that does not necessarily necessarily mean awe. It's
interesting the גמרא Gemara says something that כובד ראש koved rosh is
immediately interpreted but even before even besides the idea of bitterness you
know sort of a being of a very sort of you know
anguished soul it's translated as awe as trembling. There could be a
difference between seriousness of purpose and this awe and trembling.
Where does the word why do you suppose the word bitterness was
used in the first place? I never think of חנה Chana from
that perspective in that moment of you
know she was going through.
I don't bitter I think now in modern bitter means like bitter
resentful right so maybe there's a better translation but she's a very
anguished soul anguished better that's a wonderful word okay let's use anguished.
I mean I was just translating literally the word מרה mara but
I think it had different connotations in English so anguished okay. Anyway
but even anguished where do you see you know anyway it's interesting
what the גמרא Gemara connects to this idea of seriousness of
כובד ראש koved rosh weighty head so let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes. So so the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבי נחמן
בר יצחק מהכא ella amar Rabbi Nachman bar Yitzchak mehakka from the
following verse. עבדו את ה' ביראה ivdu et Hashem beyirah fear God
in awe וגילו ברעדה vegilu bir'ada and rejoice in trembling which is
a fascinating two words which we'll get to in a minute but.
And we start with עבדו את ה' ביראה, Ivdu et Hashem b'yirah,
fear God or serve God in awe, and that is prayer is
service of God. רש"י Rashi here again, although the גמרא Gemara does
not do it, I believe רש"י Rashi connects it to the קרבנות.
korbanos תפילה שהיא לנו במקום עבודה עשו אותה ביראה. Tefilah she-hee lanu
b'makom avodah asu osah b'yirah. תפילה tefilla which serves us in the
place of עבודה avodah seems to allude to קרבנות korbanos which are
classically עבודה. avodah. You don't have to make the קרבן korban link,
but nevertheless the sense of awe, one approaches God with a sense
of awe, and that's what we're assuming means this כובד ראש. koved
rosh. Yes. Yes.
I just want to look at the phrase אבינו שבשמים Avinu she-ba-shamayim
in the משנה Mishnah which is, I think, the first time that
we've seen in the משנה, Mishnah, right, that God is referred to
as father. As father. And
but there's a contrast, God is the father and you have to
stop,
you can't stop even for a king
while
you're communicating with your father, but then the גמרא Gemara continues viewing
God as a king, as fear and as dread, and they lose
the
father, the parent, which is that more intimate sense, right. It's a
good point that there's generally that tension, you know, אבינו מלכנו Avinu
Malkenu like we're about to say, you know, very soon in the
הימים הנוראים, ha-Yamim ha-Noraim, that double sense of closeness and right,
closeness and parent and father, and then the awe and the distance
of the king. It's a very good point and here we are
definitely emphasizing more that king and that distance and awe and fear,
that is correct, that's a very good point.
And yet you know something when you think about royalty and the
children of royalty, there is that, there is that tension between a
prince or princess, who the king is to that princess, the king
but also the father and there is a certain deference because this
is still the king.
Right. Right. Right, and you do have those, that double, that double
aspect. That is correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara shifts a
little to this end of the phrase, so we've proved it by
the beginning, עבדו את ה' ביראה. Ivdu et Hashem b'yirah. But now
we switch to the end of וגילו ברעדה, v'gilu b'ra'adah, which is,
which is rejoice in trembling, which is a very sort of fascinating
phrase, and let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
מאי וגילו ברעדה, Mai v'gilu b'ra'adah, what do you make of this
phrase rejoice in trembling? אמר רב אדא בר מתנא אמר רבא Amar
Rav Adda bar Matna amar Rava or אמר רבה, amar Rabbah, excuse
me, במקום גילה שם תהא רעדה, B'makom gilah sham tehei ra'adah, in
the place of rejoicing, there should be trembling. תוספות Tosafot says that
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk really means that at that,
when you will rejoice, תוספות Tosafot later says when the day of
trembling comes, meaning when the יום הדין Yom Ha-Din comes, you will
rejoice if you have spent your life serving God. But here we're
actually saying that no, the actual service of God brings these two
modes together, maybe it's a little bit of what רבקה Rivka was
doing about the sort of אבינו Avinu and the מלכנו Malkenu or
a little bit of what the גמרא Gemara said before about, you
know, there's a sense of כבוד kavod and dressing up nicely, you're
standing before God, a certain pride in your prayer. So, you know,
there's the, there's, so there's a sense of both being in a
sense of awe in the presence of God and trembling, and also
in the sense of intimacy and joy in being able to connect
to God, and both of those are coming together. So אביי הוה
יתיב קמיה דרבה, Abaye hava yasiv kamei d'Rabbah, אביי Abaye was standing
in front of רבה, Rabbah, sitting in front of רבה Rabbah really,
וחזייה דהוה קבדח טובא, v'chazyei d'hava ka-badach tuva, and he saw רבה
Rabbah was like, you know, very joy, was like laughing, having a
really good time, and this wasn't in דאבנינג, davening, this was presumably
just in during the שיעור, shiur, during learning. So אמר וגילו ברעדה
כתיב. Amar v'gilu b'ra'adah ksiv. Now אביי Abaye was רבה's Rabbah's student,
so it's interesting he's actually giving רבה Rabbah a little מוסר mussar
and he says, it says וגילו ברעדה, v'gilu b'ra'adah, you should rejoice
in trembling, presumably a general question about our stance in our serving
of God, not just in our תפילה. tefilla So it's okay that
you could be a little bit joyful in your עבודת השם, avodas
Hashem, but but there needs to be some sense of awe. You're
having too good of a time, you're falling off the chair in
laughter. אמר ליה, Amar leih, so he said to him, אנא תפילין
מנחנא, Ana tfillin manachna, I'm wearing תפילין. tfillin. Oh well that explains
it. So רש"י Rashi says, if you take a look at רש"י,
Rashi, it
says והן עדות שממשלת קוני ומרותו, v'hein eidus she-memsheles koni u-maruso, some
say ושררתו, u-serarato, עלי. alai. The fact that I'm wearing תפילין tfillin
keeps that puts me in that context of awe. I I don't
forget the fact that I am in the presence of God, I
have תפילין, tfillin, so I can actually laugh at a good joke
and have a good time and have that גילה, gilah, and the
רעדה ra'adah does, you know, is always kept in my mind, that
presence of God because I am wearing the תפילין. tfillin.
You could even take it as I'm about to put on תפילין
tfillin and, you know, and I'm happy about the doing the מצווה.
mitzvah.
Oh, I don't know about that. Anyway, I don't I don't know
if the grammar supports that. ר' ירמיה הוה יתיב קמיה דר' זירא,
Rav Yirmiyah hava yasiv kamei d'Rabbi Zeira, ר' ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah was
sitting in front of ר' זירא, Rabbi Zeira, וחזייה דהוה קבדח טובא,
v'chazyei d'hava ka-badach tuva, he saw that he was like laughing a
lot, אמר ליה בכל עצב יהיה מותר כתיב, Amar leih b'chol etzev
yiheyeh mosar ksiv, with all of the, you know, with all anguish
it shall be a lot, it's sufficient, meaning that you're supposed to
have have a lot of
anguish. אמר ליה אנא תפילין מנחנא, Amar leih ana tfillin manachna, same
thing I'm wearing תפילין, tfillin, that does enough to give me that
sense of maybe of anguish or seriousness. or awe in my serving
of God. This is actually quite interesting, you know, that general sense
you now extended beyond תפילה tefilla that that we always have to
be in some kind of ongoing sense of awe through, you know,
throughout the day. At least some sense of awareness of God. One
could say nowadays maybe that at least for men is what the
כיפה, kippah, since we don't wear תפילין tefillin the whole day, is
what the כיפה's kippah meant to replace, you know, but there's some
sense here it seems the concern is is that, you know, you
have to maintain a consciousness of God at all times. At least
the way I would read it. Not that there's a point in
being anguished or sad, but at least that sense of a consciousness
of God. מר בריה דרבינא עבד הלולא לבריה. Mar beireh deRavina avad
hilula levreih. So Mar the son of Ravina
made a wedding feast for his son, a wedding party. חזנהו לרבנן
דהוו קבדחי טובא. chazanhu lerabanan dehavu kabadechi tuva. He saw the rabbis
were having too good of a time, too good of a time.
They were jesting, they were laughing a lot, they were having a
good time. So אייתי כסא דמוקרא בת ארבע מאה זוזי. aiti kasa
demokra bat arba mea zuzei. He brought a glass, a chalice that
was worth four hundred zuzei, which was a lot of money, ותבר
קמייהו, utevar kamaiahu, and he, presumably, that's an exaggeration, he shattered it
in their presence. Right.
ומתעצבי. umitatzvei. Right.
בל תשחית. bal tashchit. It was important for a religious purpose. And
they became very upset and anguished. So he said, good, you weren't
having too good of a time. רב אשי עבד הלולא לבריה. Rav
Ashi avad hilula levreih. Rav Ashi made a wedding feast for his
son. חזנהו לרבנן דהוו קבדחי טובא. chazanhu lerabanan dehavu kabadechi tuva. He
saw the rabbis were laughing too much. אייתי כסא דזוגיתא חיורתא. aiti
kasa dezugita chivarta.
He brought a glass of white, a chalice, a cup of white
glass, which is very expensive, ותבר קמייהו ומתעצבי. utevar kamaiahu umitatzvei. And
he broke it in front of them and they were sad. So
he said, good. Okay, now if you look in תוספות, Tosafot, אייתי
כסא דזוגיתא חיורתא, aiti kasa dezugita chivarta, תוספות Tosafot says, מכאן נהגו
לשבר זכוכית בנישואין. mikan nahagu leshaber zechuchit benisuin.
Here's our custom to break a glass at a wedding feast. So
we normally say it's based on, you know, right, אם לא אעלה
את ירושלים על ראש שמחתי, im lo aaleh et Yerushalayim al rosh
simchati,
but it's interesting, you know, it's the same concept that we're not
supposed to be overly joyous, but it's interesting that normally we say
not to be overly joyous in the sense of the חורבן. churban.
We have to always remember we're not in a fully redeemed state,
that there's a חורבן המקדש. churban hamikdash. We can't think that we've
reached, you know, some, you know, that this is the height of
our joy. Here it's different. Here it's not about חורבן. churban. Here
it's about just a sense of always in the presence of God.
And that that sense of always feeling one's sense in the presence
of God requires a certain sort of seriousness at all times, a
certain consciousness at all times, which is pretty heavy, you know, that
general sense about, you know, that you're having too good of a
time, we're going to break some precious thing just to get you
more serious. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, אמרו ליה
רבנן לרב המנונא זוטי בהילולא דמר בריה דרבינא. amru lei rabanan leRav
Hamnuna Zuti behilula deMar beireh deRavina. So he's in similar mode here
about not having too good of a time. The rabbis said to
this person, Rav Hamnuna Zuti, in the wedding feast of Mar the
son of Ravina, לישרי לן מר, lishrei lan mar, sing for us
a song. So אמר להו, amar lehu, so here's the song he
sang for them, ווי לן דמיתנן, ווי לן דמיתנן. vai lan demitnan,
vai lan demitnan. Woe for us that we're going to die, woe
for us that we're going to die. Okay, perfect. That was just
a song, that was just the song we were hoping for. Okay.
So אמרו ליה אנן מה נעני בתרך. amru lei anan ma naani
batrach. So they
said to him, what's the refrain? What should we respond to you?
So he said, אמר
להו, amar lehu, he said to them, הי תורה והי מצוה דמגנו
לן. hei Torah vehei mitzvah demagnu lan. Where is the תורה, Torah,
where is the מצוה mitzvah that will protect us? So meaning that's
the refrain and therefore what, you know, remember basically remember that you're
going to die and that your life is like אדם לעמל יולד.
adam leamal yulad. You're here to serve God, you're here to work
hard, you're here to learn תורה, Torah, to do מצוות, mitzvot, and
that's what you have to always be thinking. Don't try, don't have
too good of a time.
I mean, I think this is still a question for women. First
of all, were these rabbis drinking?
I have no idea.
No, they were definitely, there
was definitely drinking that went on
in הילולא hilula in wedding feasts. But even if these rabbis were
really happy and they were not drinking, כל הכבוד kol hakavod to
them that they
were happy that
a new life, a new family is about to be created. And
to me, to make these remarks, it's just outrageous only because it
doesn't mean they don't know what sorrow is. I mean, I love
this construct of breaking of a glass, at our greatest joy we
feel sorrow, and I really feel that even if we had a
third temple, we should be breaking of a glass. But you know
what? If they weren't drinking, that's just the way they should have
been: filled with joy. Okay.
I have a question.
All these rabbis are at the end of the אמורא Amora period.
Is there something going on in Persia that was causing them to
be so depressed?
I don't know. It's a good question. Maybe the opposite. Maybe things
were getting to be too good and they were forgetting in a
sense of, you know, about, I mean, I'm serious, you could argue
the opposite. In the Persian period, things, I mean, the rabbis in
בבל Bavel had it very good. If you're in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael at this time, you know, you don't need to remember that
you're in גלות. galut. Exactly. So maybe that is the point, you
know, when you have it too successful and you're too good and
you actually are forgetting a little bit about your seriousness of purpose
in this life. So other than...
So other than what we do for like wedding where you do
the breaking of the glass and also when you build a new
house and you leave that bit of un-plastered wall, that's זכר לחורבן,
Zecher Lechurban, but is any of this translated into normative הלכה? Halacha?
I mean if let's say you go to a comedy club, are
you over an איסור Issur like you know?
No, but I mean you know whatever, you have this general broad
statement as we're going to say אסור לאדם למלא שחוק פיו. Assur
Leadom Limalay Sechok Piv. No, right, but is that cited in הלכה?
Halacha. Like, well, it is, but in those general sort of מדות
Middos type of things, not in like, you know there's all certain
questions about how these sort of general sort of guidelines, you know,
are treated the same as הלכה. Halacha. But we'll see the next
line does get brought in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch if that's what
you mean by הלכה.
Halacha, Yeah. How are we supposed to respond to that? That they're
agreeing or disagreeing?
I think it's they're a little I don't know, it's hard to
know, seems like a little dumbfounded like, what do we respond to
that? You know.
Is there anything of this that we can do to add? We
agree?
Or yeah, I don't, I have no idea. It's not clear. But
you know it seems that his response at least was sort of
saying it's not that you're supposed to go through life feeling miserable,
but you're supposed to realize that like life is short and we
have to use it serving God, you know, that sort of translated
into something purposeful. Okay, so let's see as the גמרא gemara. continues.
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Mishum
Rabbi Shimon Ben Yochai. So Rabbi Yochanan in the name of Shimon
Bar Yochai, this is quoted at least in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan
Aruch. אסור לאדם שימלא שחוק פיו בעולם הזה. Assur Leadom Shimalay Sechok
Piv Baolam Hazeh. A person is forbidden for instance to fill sort
of laughter, his mouth with laughter in this world. Meaning again, overly
so. שנאמר אז ימלא שחוק פינו ולשוננו
רנה. Shene'emar Az Yimalay Sechok Pinu Uleshonenu Rinah. At the time of
redemption will our mouths be filled with with laughter and our tongues
with with rejoicing. אימתי? Eimasai? When? בזמן שיאמרו בגוים הגדיל ה' לעשות
עם אלה. Bizman Sheyomru Bagoyim Higdil Hashem Laasos Im Eleh.
When they say amongst the nations, God has done greatly with these
people, meaning at the time of redemption. So אמרו ליה לריש לקיש.
Amru Lay LeReish Lakish. They said about Reish Lakish. So this was
just said by Rabbi Yochanan in the name of Shimon Bar Yochai.
So they said by Reish Lakish שמימיו. Shemiyamav. By the way, these
are thinkers from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and the name of תנאים.
Tannaim.
So they did not, the people living in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
did not need to be reminded not to be too joyous. Anyway,
שמימיו לא מלא שחוק פיו בעולם הזה. Shemiyamav Lo Milay Sechok Piv
Baolam Hazeh.
Reish Lakish made sure never to have his, to be like overly,
you know, filled with laughter מכי שמיע מרבי יוחנן רבה. Michi Shamiah
Merabbi Yochanan Rabbah. From the time he heard it from Rabbi Yochanan,
which means beforehand he was having able to have a good time.
But once he heard Rabbi Yochanan, from the time about that time
on, he made sure not to ever not to get too joyous.
So this is interesting. It does take this question about standing before
God, which demands very heightened consciousness and awareness, and now is translating
this as about a sense of like constant consciousness of God to
lead to a certain seriousness of purpose at all times, which on
the one hand is a beautiful idea. You know, שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch begins with שויתי ה' לנגדי תמיד. Shivisi Hashem Lenegdi Samid. And
that from the moment you get up in the morning, that sense
of awareness that you're always in the presence of God wherever you
are, which is obviously very important in terms of general religious consciousness.
But you know, there's also a place in which you need space
in order to live, you know, and not you know, there's times
you can demand a very serious and focus on that, and there's
times you have to give people a little, you know, arm room
so that they can, you know, so that they can live a
normal life. So the גמרא Gemara here is not saying that every
moment of your life you need כובד ראש, Koved Rosh, but they're
just saying that it should not become excessive laughter. There has to
be an element of consciousness of God at all times. So it
is important just to sort of recognize that it's trying, it's not
I think demanding the same seriousness that one has during תפילה tefillah
at all times, but just let's not get carried away. Let's limit
it to some degree. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara gets back
to the state of mind in
דאוונינג. davening. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין עומדין להתפלל לא מתוך דין
ולא מתוך דבר הלכה אלא מתוך הלכה פסוקה. Ein Omdin Lehispallel Lo
Mitoch Din Velo Mitoch Devar Halacha Ela Mitoch Halacha Pesukah. Now this
is different than the משנה Mishnah which says you stand מתוך כובד
ראש, koved rosh, seriousness of purpose, which now we're saying it has
meant like a certain sense of awe. Now we're talking about something
different. It might be seen as achieving the same goals, but the
גמרא Gemara will actually say later that this is a different approach,
that you only get up from to דאוון, davven, not in the
middle of judgment, like you're sort of you know having some דין
תורה Din Torah with somebody, you're actually sitting in judgment, or from
הלכה, Halacha, again similar type of an issue, somebody's asking you a
הלכתית Halachic question and you're analyzing it and you're thinking back and
forth, so your mind is very sort of intertwined you know sort
of occupied, preoccupied with these questions and analysis, you know, and there
your head is somewhere else even though that somewhere else is an
important מצוה Mitzvah and הלכה, Halacha, your head shouldn't be somewhere else.
אלא מתוך הלכה פסוקה. Ela Mitoch Halacha Pesukah. You stand up from
a sort of a cut ruling, a simple accepted הלכה, halakha that's
what you sort of learn before you get up to דאוון. davven.
Let's take a look. והיכי דמי הלכה פסוקה? Veheichi Dami Halacha Pesukah?
What is meant by הלכה פסוקה? Halacha Pesukah? What's an example of
it? אמר אביי כי הא דרבי זירא. Amar Abaye Ki Ha DeRabbi
Zeira. Like Rabbi Zeira. So this ties in our last מסכת Masechet
of ש"ס Shas with now ברכות, Berachos, although we got this we
learned all of נדה Niddah and this one line of Rabbi Zeira
which totally transforms all of הלכות נדה Hilchos Niddah nowadays was kept
to the very end of the מסכת. Masechet. And now we're revisiting
it. Says Rabbi Zeira, בנות ישראל החמירו על עצמן. Benos Yisrael Hechmiru
Al Atzman. Jewish women took a stringency... upon themselves, שאפילו רואות טיפת
דם כחרדל, she'afilu ro'os tipas dam kehardal, even they saw a drop
of blood as small as a mustard seed, and as someone says,
and even smaller, even the tiniest drop of blood, יושבות עליו שבעה
נקיים, yoshvos alav shivah neki'im, has to wait seven clean days. Although
according to the Torah, a woman only waits seven days from the
onset of bleeding, even if all the days were bleeding, as long
as she stops right before the end of the seventh day she
goes to the מקוה. mikvah. And if it's during her זבה zavah
period, she would only need seven clean days if she saw three
days consecutively. At a certain period, the practice became that even one
drop of blood was treated as though the woman became a זבה
zavah and required seven clean days, and that's what we do nowadays.
This is an example of הלכה פסוקה. halacha pesuka. Let's take a
look at a couple of הלכה פסוקה halacha pesuka and then we'll
discuss of what is meant by this category of הלכה פסוקה. halacha
pesuka. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
what?
דם? dam?
זבה? zavah?
Yeah, a woman sees a drop of blood, she's automatically זב. zav.
By a man, there's a difference of what the fluid is. By
a woman, נדה niddah or זבה, zavah, it's always blood, it's a
question of what time during the month. Okay.
Is that what men should be thinking about before they pray? Well,
everything in Judaism...
Let's see some other examples, maybe it's what the women should be
thinking about. Women are also חייבין בתפילה. chayavin bitfillah. Okay, I don't
know, but let's take a look, let's see some examples. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, רבא אמר כי הא דרב הושעיא, Rava amar
ki ha deRav Hoshaia,
like the teaching of רב הושעיא, Rav Hoshaia, דאמר רב הושעיא, de'amar
Rav Hoshaia, because רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaia said, מערים אדם על תבואתו
ומכניסה במוץ שלה כדי שתהא בהמתו אוכלת ופטורה מן המעשר. ma'arim adam
al tevu'aso umachnisah bemotz shellah kedei shetehei behemto ocheles upeturah min hama'aser.
Not necessarily the easiest הלכות. halachos Okay, a person could be, can
scheme regarding his grain and bring it in while it's still in
its chaff into the threshing floor in order that his animal should
eat and be exempt from מעשר. ma'aser. What does that mean? So
there's a lot you have to understand to what this means. Number
one is, so a grain
before grain becomes what's called הוקבע למעשר, hukva lema'aser, gone through the
process where now it's obligated in מעשר, ma'aser, you are allowed to
eat from it without taking
תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros if you do it in a non-fixed way,
not אכילת קבע achilas keva like you're sitting down to a meal,
but אכילת עראי. achilas arai. Included in אכילת עראי, achilas arai, a
non-sort of set fixed eating, is feeding it to your animal. Then
you're not eating, you're feeding it to your animal. Now, that's if
it's out there in the field. When does it become obligated in
מעשר ma'aser that you cannot use it at all until you take
תרומות ומעשרות? terumos u'ma'asros? When you do מירוח, miruach, which is sort
of like the smoothing over of the pile after it's been threshed
and winnowed and the whole thing, and then it's been brought into
the house or brought into the whatever, the barn or wherever you're
going to store the grain. So if you reverse the order, however,
bring it into the house, to the barn, before the whole sort
of winnowing and the smoothing, and then you do that in the
barn, then it actually never becomes fully obligated in מעשר. ma'aser. And
therefore, if you reverse the order and you did this trick, you
can use the whole pile of grain to feed your animal. You
can't use it actually to sit down to a meal with, but
you never have to take תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. You can't use
it.
So why is it talking about feeding your animal? Even you!
Even you if you do it temporarily in an אכילת עראי, achilas
arai, like you snack on it. But you cannot sit down to
a meal with it, you cannot do an אכילת קבע. achilas keva.
But you can feed the whole pile to your grain. So that
is something that you can work out, and that is an example
of
הלכה פסוקה. halacha pesuka. So again, a little strange, both of these
examples. Let's read the third one and then we'll talk about it.
ואי בעית אימא, Vei ba'is eima, and a third example is כי
הא דרב הונא, ki ha deRav Huna, like what רב הונא Rav
Huna teaches. דאמר רב הונא אמר רב זביד, De'amar Rav Huna amar
Rav Zevid, because רב הונא Rav Huna says in the name of
רב זביד, Rav Zevid, המקיז דם בבהמת קדשים, hamakiz dam be'vehemas kodashim,
if somebody lets blood by an animal that is sanctified as a
sacrifice, אסור בהנאה ומועלין בו. assur behana'ah u'mo'alin bo.
Although normally the rule is that blood used for animal sacrifices, there's
no מעילה, me'ilah, that because the blood that will go on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, you slaughter an animal, you catch the blood, it's going
to be thrown on the מזבח, mizbeiach, there's no מעילה, me'ilah, there's
no, you know, קרבן that has to be brought for misuse and
deriving benefit from that blood. It's a דרשה drasha that says אני
נתתיו לכם על המזבח לכפר. ani nesasiv lachem al hamizbeiach lechaper. I've
given you the blood to atone, to atone but not for מעילה.
me'ilah. There's no transgression of מעילה. me'ilah. If it is blood that
is not being used for that purpose, like you had to let
the blood from this animal because it was going to die and
they thought that the way you sort of would do a certain
types of medical treatments was to let blood, then that blood actually,
the same way there'd be מעילה me'ilah by using the animal for
personal purposes, there's מעילה me'ilah for using the blood. So if you
actually did that and let blood and took this blood from this
sanctified animal, you cannot derive benefit, and if you do, you transgress
מעילה me'ilah and you have to bring the קרבן מעילה. korban me'ilah.
That is a third example. Okay, not very simple cases. So רבנן
עבדי כמתניתין, rabbanan avdi kemasnishin, and thus ending this
point, the rabbis, meaning the students of the ישיבה, yeshiva, acted like
a משנה. Mishna. Their focus was on כובד ראש, koved rosh, seriousness
of purpose, awe if you would. רב אשי עביד כברייתא. Rav Ashi
avid ke'braisa. רב אשי Rav Ashi did like the ברייתא, braisa, to
stand up מתוך הלכה פסוקה. mitoch halacha pesuka. So let me say
a few things about this. Number one, the very fact that it
says some people acted like the משנה, Mishna, some like the ברייתא,
braisa, shows that these are not such different ways to get to
כובד הראש. koved harosh. It's serving some different purpose. And one imagines
that first of all, the most obvious different purpose it's serving is
talking about people that are spending their day learning. Okay, so meaning
about the sort of Rabbinic class. So what do you guys do?
You, what you know think well maybe if I'm sitting and learning
I can just in the middle of my learning I'll I'm already
seriousness of purpose. I'm spending my time sitting and learning. So that
already gives myself I'll just you know get up and start דאווענינג
davening right away. So for the people that would be sitting and
learning it'd say no no no by the way not some type
a type of learning can get you too distracted and there has
to be a certain type of a learning that's going to put
you like in the right mind frame. Now that being said I
have to tell you that these הלכות halachos are not simple points.
You know they're like like I it took me a minute to
explain the background of each one and that was super fast. It's
not like saying a simple הלכה halakha like you have to I
don't know דאווען daven three times a day. That's an interest that's
an easy הלכה פסוקה halakha pesuka you know. So I don't really
know why these are sort of chosen other than that like you
could argue that for some people you know if you're like if
you're if you're really good in a topic and you're deep within
a topic if something is too simplistic it doesn't like sort of
necessarily focus your mind in the same way. You know if you're
like you know if you were a you know physicist and we
said okay right before you get up to דאווען daven. you should
say you know what is it like you know
speed equals distance over time. Like oh you know it's like so
ABCs it doesn't focus but you say something that's like okay there
is a little complexity to it but it's very you know but
it still it still clear and it focuses you and it's a
bottom line. So maybe that's why this has a greater degree of
complexity than we would have expected because maybe a certain amount is
needed you know if you're talking about people that are you know
you know serious תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim they need that but then
at the end it's very bottom line once you actually say it.
I don't know but that's just my speculation. The other thing I'll
say about this is is that I wonder if the point here
about הלכה פסוקה halakha pesuka is not just like it should not
be other types of learning that distract you but maybe there's actually
a sense about what is that framing of דאווענינג. davening. You know
is the framing of דאווענינג davening is it just here get yourself
focused or is there a framing of דאווענינג davening that's actually ideal
to have הלכה halakha learning of some type of הלכה halakha leading
into תפילה that there is some sense of you know that the
sort of seriousness of purpose is not just I'm about to stand
before God but seriousness of purpose like seriousness of purpose in life.
So being involved in הלכה halakha and knowing that my life is
dictated by the laws and concerns about these details and so on
that is sort of the right framing of that sense of now
you approach God because you leave a you leave you've essentially made
a statement that you are you know you're involved in a purposeful
type of God-directed life. And that then becomes the right framing for
leading into the תפילה. So that's sort of a little different than
just focusing you know psychologically but actually making a statement about how
we're framing one's דאווענינג. davening Yes?
I was just thinking in the same kind of way because if
you're really brilliant and this is what your life is, you can
be someone who learns very simply without any struggle and maybe doesn't
really connect to God in all this. It's an exercise. But when
there's a humility involved and you realize that all this is in
service of this respect and awe of God. It's a very different
kind of tension.
Right, right, right. So I like that. So your point is that
right that you that by connecting the two you're connecting your sense
of service and your in your learning to your service in your
תפילה. Right, right rather than just saying oh this is דאווענינג we
have to get done with it let's move on type of thing.
Right.
So element thought that these רבנן rabbanan did like the ברייתא braisa
seems to imply that they held that the הלכה halakha is that
you really have to learn a הלכה halacha before you דאווען.
Now רב אשי Rav Ashi you mean רב אשי Rav Ashi did
like the ברייתא. braisa. Right, right. But again the question is does
it actually does it mean for everybody? Does it mean you have
a choice? You know it might seem the message at the end
seems to be you have your choice sort of of which one
works better for you. עבדי כברייתא avadi ke-braisa didn't mean they פסקן
paskin like the משנה mishna they פסקן paskin like the ברייתא. braisa.
No they
they saw these as two choices, two options and they the רבנן
did this and רב אשי Rav Ashi did the other, yes. Oh.
We actually have similar thing in the סידור siddur after
ברכת התורה.
birkat hatora.
Yes but that's not תפילה here always means שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei
So as we're going to see the one thing we do before
שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei. the one time we have a choice to
do something before שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei, is מנחה mincha because שחרית
shacharis and מעריב maariv are basically fixed and it's about גאולה geula
and תפילה. מנחה mincha is where sort of if we're going to
say something as it were you know we have a choice and
we actually have adopted the practice of doing אשרי ashrei which isn't
in the גמרא. Gemara Okay so that if you would אשרי יושבי
ביתך ashrei yoshvei veisecha seems to be sort of a little more
of an embodiment of the משנה mishna than הלכה פסוקה halakha pesuka
you know a sense of being in God's presence and we'll see
אשרי ashrei coming up a little
later. Presumably. Let's keep on going. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין
עומדים להתפלל לא מתוך עצבות. Ein omdim lehitpalel lo mitoch atzvut. You
don't stand up to דאוון daven from being now remember we mentioned
before מרה נפש marah nefesh of sort of of anguish. Now we're
saying you don't stand up to דאוון daven out of sadness, if
you're sad about something, ולא מתוך עצלות velo mitoch atzlut or out
of laziness of like I guess it means oy you gotta stand
up and דאוון daven now like, so you're not obviously in the
right mind frame and energy, ולא מתוך שחוק velo mitoch sechok which
is all a bit before you shouldn't be you know too much
after having said a great joke go right into דאוונינג, davening, ולא
מתוך שיחה velo mitoch sicha not just סתם stam שמוזינג, schmoozing, ולא
מתוך קלות ראש velo mitoch kalut rosh not of lightheadedness,
levity, which seems to be sort of the previous things some of
them seem to have been examples of that, ולא מתוך דברים בטלים
velo mitoch dvarim betelim well that's also just sort of talking of
nonsense, אלא מתוך שמחה של מצוה ela mitoch simcha shel mitzvah out
of a joy of a מצוה mitzvah which is interesting. What exactly
does that mean? Let's keep on reading and see what we get
with that. Well let's take a look.
So I mean well okay let's look at רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says שמחה, simcha, רש"י Rashi says כגון דברי תנחומים של תורה. kegon
divrei tanchumim shel Torah. So you understand שמחה של מצוה simcha shel
mitzvah really means שמחה simcha of תורה, Torah. כגון סמוך לגאולת מצרים
kegon samuch l'geulat Mitzrayim or סמוך לתהילה לדוד samuch l'tehila l'David ששבח
ותנחומים sheshvach v'tanchumim כגון רצון יראיו יעשה kegon ratzon yereiav ya'aseh שומע
ה' את כל אוהביו shomeia Hashem et kol ohavav ומכל צרותינו הושיענו
umikol tzaroteinu hoshieinu ערבית לא יטוש ה' עמו. Arvit lo yitosh Hashem
amo. So רש"י Rashi by right, so רש"י Rashi tries to
tie this in to our structure of דאוונינג davening and by reading
פסוקים psukim that speak about our joyous, our positive relationship with God.
God observes those that love, you know, protects those that love Him
and so on, that is a שמחה של מצוה. simcha shel mitzvah.
Now מצוה mitzvah normally for us doesn't evoke like saying פסוקים, psukim,
it seems like doing a מצוה mitzvah but that's the way רש"י
Rashi reads it. And again that's very different going back to this
issue. Is it awe? So here it's not exactly the awe, you
don't have כובד ראש, you don't have the הלכה halacha context which
is maybe specifically for תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. You have this sense
about joy, about this relationship with God but then frames it. Okay.
Not the sort of levity, but a joy of that sense of
that closeness and that intimacy.
What?
Yes, but it's different than the emphasis before which was about awe.
שמחה של מצוה simcha shel mitzvah or שמחה simcha more the way
רש"י Rashi frames it of this closeness with God is a very
different type of framing.
I don't know.
No, well she certainly yeah but she oh you mean that sense
about about צער, tza'ar, right, right.
So is she the model for prayer?
Yeah that's a good question. I mean I you know, עצבות atzvut
could also I mean, it's a good question whether if it's an
עצבות atzvut that then is an עצבות atzvut that is like turning
and pouring out your pain to God, it's hard to imagine that
the גמרא Gemara is sort of rejecting that. I assume it means
that you're distracted by other things, not that you're sort of directing
that pain in your prayer to God. But it is, the גמרא
Gemara does have a couple of different sort of models here and
they seem to more be like different options than directly competing. Let's
see a little bit more. וכן לא יפטר אדם מחבירו לא מתוך
שיחה vechen lo yipater adam mechaveiro lo mitoch sicha and also when
you leave your friend after having spent time together it should not
just be that you've like the last thing you do is you
were just sort of סתם stam שמוזינג schmoozing together, ולא מתוך שחוק
velo mitoch sechok or having a good laugh together. You're allowed to
do that during but not the last type of thing you say.
ולא מתוך קלות ראש velo mitoch kalut rosh
or too much levity, ולא מתוך דברים
בטלים
velo
mitoch dvarim
betelim or like you know nonsense talk.
רש"י Rashi says the difference between שיחה sicha and דברים בטלים dvarim
betelim is שיחה sicha is like ליצנות leitzanut which is even worse,
it's like mocking. Anyway, אלא מתוך דבר הלכה ela mitoch dvar halacha
which is interesting. We had just said שמחה של מצוה simcha shel
mitzvah it says דבר הלכה dvar halacha which is getting back to
the earlier thing. So if you take a look at the הגר"א
Hagra on the side, it says רשום קו על תיבת דבר הלכה
שמחה של מצוה. rashum kav al teivat dvar halacha simcha shel mitzvah.
So the הגר"א Hagra makes it consistent with what we just said.
I haven't checked the other manuscripts whether they have that or not,
but at least the הגר"א Hagra wants to make it because we
said וכן. vechen. So we're saying so when you leave you should
leave in the sense of some joy, some מצוה mitzvah joy. Let's
see the example. שכן מצינו בנביאים הראשונים shechen matzinu binevi'im harishonim we
found by the early prophets שסיימו דבריהם בדברי שבח ותנחומים sheshiyimu divreihem
bedivrei shevach vetanchumim
that when you come to the end of the prophets, except with
one or two notable exceptions, like like ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, anyway they ended
on a very positive note about our relationship with God. So again
שמחה של מצוה simcha shel mitzvah has more to do about a
positive way about talking about you know our relationship with God. So
if you would it should be like you know God should be
with you in all our endeavors, you know, something like that which
has a sense about expressing the joy about our about God and
our closeness with God. וכן תנא מרי בריה דרב הונא בריה דרב
ירמיה בר אבא vechen tana Mari breih deRav Huna breih deRav Yirmiya
bar Abba similarly the הגר"א Hagra takes out the וכן vechen just
says תנא מרי בריה. tana Mari breih. We taught in a ברייתא
braita of מרי בריה דרב הונא Mari breih deRav Huna the son
of רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב ירמיה בר אבא.
Rav Yirmiya bar Abba. אל יפטר אדם מחבירו אלא מתוך דבר הלכה.
al yipater adam mechaveiro ela mitoch dvar halacha. See that's why the
הגר"א Hagra takes out the word וכן vechen because he sees on
תנא tana we're talking about שמחה של מצוה, simcha shel mitzvah, שמחה
simcha about that connection to God, and now we're going back to
the earlier theme about הלכה halacha that when you actually leave somebody
you should end with a
דבר הלכה. dvar halacha. שמתוך כך זוכרהו shemitoch kach zochreihu because based
on that he'll. remember you and also a way about it'll frame
the connection in this, it's not just סתם stam giving you good
advice about how to get remembered by your friends, but it also
frames the whole connection through this way of learning and through this
דבר הלכה. devar halacha. כי הא דרב כהנא ki ha d'Rav Kahana
like רב כהנא Rav Kahana אלוייה לרב שימי בר אשי avyei l'Rav
Shimi bar Ashi מפומנא miPumna עד בית צניסא. ad Beit Tzanisa.
He accompanied רב שימי בר אשי. Rav Shimi bar Ashi. It's another
הלכה halacha that when your guest leaves you're supposed to accompany them
out the door. So he accompanied him all the way from פומנא
Pumna run to this place called בית צניסא Beit Tzanisa of בבל.
Bavel. Of בבל. Bavel. כי מטא להתם ki mata l'hasam when he
came to there, אמר
ליה מר ודאי דאמרי אינשי amar lei mar vaday d'amri inshi so
he said to him, master, this is definitely what people say, הני
צניסא דבבל איתנהו מאדם הראשון. hani tzanisa d'Bavel isnehu m'Adam haRishon. These,
these palm trees, בית צניסא Beit Tzanisa means the place of the
palm trees of בבל. Bavel. So these palm trees, they are so
ancient, they must have come from the time of אדם הראשון Adam
haRishon ועד השתא v'ad hashta until now. אמר ליה amar lei so
רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi said to him, אדכרתן
מילתא דרבי יוסי בר חנינא. adkartan milta d'Rabbi Yose bar Chanina. You
reminded me of the teaching of רב יוסי בר חנינא. Rabbi Yose
bar Chanina. דאמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא d'amar Rabbi Yose bar Chanina
like רב יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yose bar Chanina said, מאי דכתיב
mai d'chtiv what's meant by the verse בארץ אשר לא עבר בה
איש ולא ישב אדם שם, b'eretz asher lo avar bah ish v'lo
yashav adam sham, a land that a person has never passed and
that אדם Adam has never dwelt there? וכי מאחר דלא עבר היכא
ישב v'ki me'achar d'lo avar heicha yashav if nobody has ever passed
through it, how could anybody dwell? Now of course that's the classic
poetic device in the נביאים nevi'im that it
actually first says the bigger thing and then says the lesser thing,
which is the opposite normally how we would expect, but anyway that's
a classic poetic device, but nonetheless he's asking if nobody ever passed
through it, how could anybody sit there?
אלא לומר לך ela lomar lach to tell you, כל ארץ שגזר
עליה אדם הראשון ליישוב נתיישבה, kol eretz shegazar aleha Adam haRishon l'yishuv
nisyashva,
any land, the same way all the animals passed by אדם הראשון,
Adam haRishon, אדם הראשון Adam haRishon sort of was the first urban
planner, and any land that he did not dictate should ever be
settled, like he didn't zone it, I'm teasing, any he did not
dictate that it should
be inhabited, נתיישבה nisyashva was inhabited. וכל ארץ שלא גזר עליה אדם
הראשון ליישוב לא נתיישבה, v'chol eretz shelo gazar aleha Adam haRishon l'yishuv
lo nisyashva, anyone that he did not dictate should be inhabited,
was not. So that's ולא ישב אדם שם v'lo yashav adam sham
means אדם הראשון Adam haRishon did not dictate that it should be
settled. Okay. And this is relevant because he said that these palm
trees were from אדם הראשון, Adam haRishon, so either he connected it
to אדם הראשון Adam haRishon of בבל Bavel or רש"י Rashi says
the reason there were these palm trees and they were not mowed
down and it was not settled was because אדם הראשון Adam haRishon
had dictated that it should always remain that way. For example. And
right, so this is interesting. Yes. So let's just finish this. רב
מרדכי אלוייה לרב שימי בר אשי Rav Mordechai avyei l'Rav Shimi bar
Ashi מהגרוניא ועד בי קיפי m'Hagronia v'ad Bei Kifi from Hagronia to
Bei Kifi. ואמרי לה עד בי דורא v'amri lah ad Bei Dura
and some say until בי דורא, Bei Dura, which is just talking
about the importance, not about departing with a דבר הלכה, devar halacha,
but about accompanying your guests on the
way. Actually we recently just read of course עגלה ערופה eglah arufah
and the whole point about accompanying them and so on. Now as
Michael was pointing out here, yes, it's interesting that דבר הלכה devar
halacha is pretty
elastic. That what הלכה Halakha is this? But it's some type of
a rabbinic teaching now becomes a דבר הלכה. devar halacha. Okay. So
it seems that that phrase becomes a little bit broader and then
it is again, and what is interesting I think is again this
sort of tension between a type of a rabbinic class. So if
you're like within the rabbis the way you sort of want to
end and frame it is some talking of תורה. Torah. You want
to end it with a talking of תורה. Torah, Okay. Whereas if
you're, if you're maybe not of that class, or maybe you are
of that class but you don't always have to talk תורה, you
end it with, then it's with a שמחה של מצוה, simcha shel
mitzvah, some type of a sort of more of a ברכה, bracha,
some type of a connection to the sense of our connection to
God and God's presence. So the same type of sort of options
that you have about what way you frame your דאוונען, davening, you
also getting these two options about what way to sort of end
your, when you leave a friend, which is a way of also
framing the relationship.
And the same type of two options are being offered here, similar
to the other two. What we did add though is that it's
the move away from the יראה yirah to the idea of the
שמחה, simcha, which is obviously a very important shift. Yes.
You were going to say that the גמרא Gemara about
these trees...
no it wasn't. He responded with a דבר תורה. devar Torah. I
know but he responded with a דבר תורה. devar Torah. The one
who was leaving said oh my gosh these trees look like they
were here from אדם הראשון Adam haRishon and he said oh let
me tell you a nice little דבר תורה devar Torah about that.
דבר תורה? Devar Torah? Well, I know it's hard for us to
understand, I understand it's hard for us to understand why this constitutes
a דבר תורה, devar Torah, that is true.
Does anyone ever take it like על פי סוד? al pi sod?
שמחה של מצוה Simcha shel mitzvah like give צדקה tzedakah or whatever
it is.
That doesn't seem to be the example of the גמרא Gemara when
it speaks about the נביאים nevi'im ending with שמחה של מצוה, simcha
shel mitzvah, that wasn't the case. Okay.
Right. Okay, so let's now take a look as the גמרא gemara
continues.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. המתפלל צריך שיכוין לבו לשמים. hamispallel tzarich sheyachavein
libo lashamayim. As when somebody דאוונס, davens, they have to direct their
heart to heaven. Okay. You need כוונה. kavana. אבא שאול אומר... Abba
Shaul omer... The סימן siman is
they will prepare, they will focus their heart, and then Your ears
will hear. You will listen to our תפילות tefillos if we give
it proper כוונה. kavana? And here again is the challenge of the
גמרא because תפילה is obviously much more than just reciting words. It
is prayer. Prayer means like communicating of our feelings. How do you
create הלכות about כוונה? kavana Right, which is what this משנה mishna
is trying to do. You know, in some ways before the issue
what I've been discussing about personal prayer and fixed prayer has an
element, I know, it's the battery died. Just forget it. It's whatever.
We'll recharge, we'll take, nothing to do. Anyway, so before the issue
about fixed prayer and personal prayer, personal prayer definitely emphasized that idea
of כוונה kavana, in your thoughts. But you know, you could have
a sense about your personal prayer without necessarily focusing so much on
your getting in touch with your deeper, deepest thoughts. Like we had
the people before who had their own personal prayers they added at
the end of שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei. but it became a fixed
text, right? So here to some degree that sort of fixed versus
personal, communal versus personal is the issue of also כוונה, kavana but
כוונה kavana could be somewhat independent of that. Whatever prayer you're saying,
how do you speak about getting your mindset into it, getting your
כוונה kavana? into it? How do you create הלכות about כוונה? kavana,
Okay, so this is now the גמרא is really honing in on
this. So somebody who prays has to have כוונה, kavana has to
direct their heart to Heaven. תניא, Tanya, we're taught, אמר רב יהודה,
amar Rav Yehuda, כך היה מנהגו של רבי עקיבא. kach haya minhago
shel Rabbi Akiva. Here's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva used to do.
כשהיה מתפלל עם הצבור, keshehaya mispalel im hatzibur, when he was with
the congregation, היה מקצר ועולה מפני טורח צבור. haya mekatzeir veoleh mipnei
torech tzibur. He would sort of shorten his תפילה and rise up
because of the טורח, torech, of the burden on the congregation to
go on. They were either waiting for him to finish or maybe
עולה oleh could begin, we had the phrase תפלה עולה tefilla oleh
before, when a person יורד לפני התיבה yoreid lifnei hateiva and then
he is עולה, oleh, he comes up from having led as a
שליח צבור shliach tzibur because they would lead, they would be in
some type of, they would be right in some type
of a hole, of a pit when they were leading. So maybe
he was even שליח צבור. shliach tzibur. But either way, he would
דאוון daven it short because if he was going long, everybody would
wait for him. Maybe he was even the שליח צבור. shliach tzibur.
וכשהוא מתפלל בינו לבין עצמו, ucheshehu mispalel beino levein atzmo, but when
he was in private, אדם מניחו בזוית זו, adam manicho bezois zu,
he could start דאוונינג davening in one corner of the room, ומוצאו
בזוית אחרת, umotzo bezois acheres, you'd come back and he'd be done
and he'd be in the other corner of the room after the
end of his שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei, וכל כך למה, vechol kach
lama, how did that happen? מפני כריעות והשתחויות, mipnei krios vehishtachavayos, because
he would be שוקלינג, shokeling, his bending and his bowing down and
he'd be שוקלינג shokeling so much, he'd end up in the other
corner of a room. So here you get the first example of
people really doing this like, you know, intense שוקלינג shokeling during דאוונינג.
davening. Now, some academics think, you know, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
very much associated with
this, with sort of mystical,
kabbalistic and a mystical sort of approach, and some think that this
also was a state of being, you know, in some type of
mystical rapture. Maybe this happened, not just through normal שוקלינג. shokeling. Okay,
that's possible, it's not clear about that. But more trans, more relevant
to us though is the contrast of צבור tzibur and יחיד and
a point I've said before and the idea of like, the difference.
One difference could just be, okay, people are waiting on me. I
have to be responsible to the people around me. I can't overly
indulge in my כוונה kavana if it has impact on other people,
right? There's always that בין אדם לחברו bein adam lachaveiro aspect as
well that you have to be sensitive to. But there could be
another point being said here as well, which is this tension between
כוונה kavana
versus, you know, a sort of a more sort of fixed ritual
and so on plays
out in different spheres. Private prayer versus communal prayer. Right, that if
you're in a community, the part, what you're being asked to give
up a little bit of your own personal subjective experience for the
sake of the communal experience. Right, that whole idea of תפלות כנגד
קרבנות tefillos keneged korbanos and communal sacrifice, and if we're going to
have an element of our תפילה being the communal prayer, praying as
a community, so it's not all about you and it's not about
your כוונה kavana here. It's a little bit more about doing what
you need to be to be part of the communal experience. And
there we ask you to rein it in a little bit. When
you're in private, then it could be all about your personal prayer
even if you're praying a fixed text, and there you're allowed to
give more latitude to your own כוונה kavana? which you would not,
which you would be asked not to do in the sense of
the צבור. tzibur. So that is what? Yeah, or in other ways
it can just be, so for example, before we had the issue
about
verbalizing your דאוונינג. davening. So you're told don't verbalize your דאוונינג davening
in the צבור tzibur because you'll distract the צבור. tzibur. So again,
does that just mean others if there's one guy דאוונינג davening next
to you, you shouldn't verbalize because you'll distract the person? Or does
that mean a broader sense that when you're in the צבור tzibur
you have to focus on the decorum and the communal experience and
that's not about you hearing you say your private דאוונינג? davening? You
have to like rein it in a little bit, there's a sense
here of a ציבור experience. If you want to go to town
fine, דאוון daven ביחידות. be-yechidus. Okay, and then becomes an interesting question
if there really is that difference, how do I choose? Should I
go to שול shul and opt more for the communal experience, or
should I דאוון daven ביחידות be-yechidus and have more כוונה? kavana And
that's a question in which gets asked the פוסקים poskim and there
are different answers. It's not surprising פוסקים poskim mostly side with the
go to שול shul have more because they because focus more on
the external sort of forms than on the internal כוונה kavana because
in general הלכה handles those external aspects better than it does the
internal type of an experience which you can't sort of quantify and
measure. Yes, Bob.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva shared with his students how he דאווענט davened
privately because he's alone and he goes out of the room.
How they know? Well they say they left him and they came
back. So maybe maybe they figured okay it's been an hour he's
got to be done now and they walk back in the room
and he was still דאווענינג but he was somewhere else in the
other corner.
Well it sounds like the example his example the גמרא might be
suggesting that the demand the requirement for כוונה kavana for interiority is
placed more appropriately when you choose to דאוון daven by yourself and
that you lift the requirement somewhat or you don't have as weighty
expectation if you're in a communal setting.
Oh you're saying the opposite.
Communal setting mitigates how much can you demand of a person if
by definition distracting.
Oh that's interesting you're saying what I'm saying in the reverse that
we make the demands in private and we lift the demands not
like we allow you in private to go you know to have
this latitude he restrains himself. Right. Maybe I hear that. That's an
interesting right an interesting way of sort of showing which is your
starting point. That's a good point. Okay let's look a little more.
אמר רבי אבא לעולם יתפלל אדם בבית שיש בו חלונות. Amar Rabbi
Abba le-olam yitpallel adam bevayit sheyesh bo chalonot. A person should always
pray in a house that has windows. שנאמר Shene-emar and now we're
going to use now we're going to start talking about models for
how one prays and before we get to חנה Chana which is
as we know the most you know common model or the famous
model thank you we're going to start with Daniel because actually it
speaks in Daniel about how he would pray on a regular basis.
So it says in Daniel וכוין פתיחן לה ve-kavin petichin leh and
the windows would be sort of he would be opposite him when
he would pray. You know by the way one should mention that
this is at least I'll just speak my personal experience you know
that there is a way in which that connectedness that is lost
when it's totally in an artificial setting. I mean you know that
you know I find when I am out in nature that sense
of sort of being connected to this greater sense of the world
of nature of God you know a certain sense of connectedness that
I never get when I am דאווענינג you know inside of a
שול shul even a שול shul that's you know very beautiful or
whatever you know different things that are done in terms of the
architecture of a שול shul that are made to sort of uplift
and inspire I still feel there's a connectedness that is lost when
you're not you know when you're inside of a building. So here
the גמרא speaks about at least being opposite a window when one
prays. יכול יתפלל אדם כל היום כולו Yachol yitpallel adam kol hayom
kulo maybe you should pray the whole day. Yes he did. כבר
מפורש על ידי דניאל Kevar meforash al yedei Daniel so it says
by Daniel וזמנין תלתא ve-zimnin telata three times you would דאוון. daven.
Again
notice by the way the fact that maybe you should דאוון daven
and quoting Daniel and not quoting קרבנות korbanos. is very much a
non קרבן model here. Other than רש"י Rashi we haven't mentioned קרבנות
korbanos at all right? It's about prayer very much as this personal
כוונה connected to God so maybe it should be all day? No
three times is enough okay morning afternoon evening those separate the day.
As an obligation?
Yeah it seems to be or right you could read it maybe
you should be allowed but it does think the simpler sense maybe
you should. יכול משבא לגולה הוא חלה Yachol misheba lagolah hu chalah
and now also seems to be a subtle sort of you know
conversation with the קרבן model. Maybe this only began after exile. Maybe
when there were קרבנות korbanos you did not pray. כבר נאמר די
הוי עבד מן קדמת דנא Kevar ne-emar di-hava avad min kadmat denah
he would pray this way from prior to this even when there
were קרבנות. korbanos We don't even say the word קרבנות korbanos interesting
we want to keep our complete focus on the prayer experience not
the קרבן and emphasizing it was even when there were even in
the past implicitly even when there were קרבנות korbanot. prayer is not
about קרבנות korbanot, necessarily. Okay.
You could read it the other way.
משבא לגולה הוא חלה
misheba lagolah hu chalah
maybe he just prayed three times a day when he came to
the גולה golah but before that maybe I think we're beyond the
three times but maybe. Okay. יכול יתפלל אדם בכל רוח שירצה Yachol
yitpallel adam bechol ruach sheyirtzeh
maybe you could דאוון daven in any direction that you want. Again
if it's about God maybe direction doesn't matter. So it says no
נגד ירושלים neged Yerushalayim towards Jerusalem. Okay which again is it towards
Jerusalem because it somehow connects to the קרבנות or is it towards
Jerusalem just because it's Jerusalem as the place of God's שכינה? Shekhinah?
Okay so again you know but the הוה אמינא hava mina here
and the answers I think are all very much pointing to תפילה
as this universal connectedness. to God, not about קרבנות. יכול יאמרם בבת
אחת yakhol yomram bevas achas of three times, maybe say them three
times, one, two, three, right in a row, כבר מפורש על ידי
דוד kvar meforash al yedei david דכתיב ערב ובקר וצהרים, dekhiv erev
uvoker vetzohorayim,
evening, morning, and day I will pray, so therefore it is three
different times during the day. יכול ישמיע קולו בתפלתו, yakhol yashmiya kolo
bitfillato, maybe your voice could be heard when you דאוון? daven? כבר
מפורש על ידי חנה, kvar meforash al yedei chana, now we move
to the חנה chana model שנאמר וקולה לא ישמע, shenne'emar vekola lo
yishama, her voice should not be heard.
יכול, yakhol, this סוגיא sugya is like this סוגיא sugya doesn't know
the other סוגיא sugya at all
that we've already discussed these issues. Right, exactly, exactly. It's as if
they're raising this
topic for the first time. Exactly.
But again, and what's beautiful about that, what I've sort of been
saying is that we're just looking at תנ"ך tanakh models, we're ignoring
קרבנות, we're basically just focusing on people who prayed, on very much
on that human religious experience of prayer, and that's our model. Okay.
Now, יכול ישאל אדם צרכיו ואחר כך יתפלל, yakhol yishal adam tzerakhav
ve'achar kach yitpallel, maybe a person should first make personal requests and
then pray? Interesting. So maybe prayer is not even called בקשה? bakashah?
Prayer is praising God. Maybe the בקשה bakashah comes, you know, it
doesn't say and then you should be משבח, meshabe'ach, then you should
be מתפלל, mitpallel, which is interesting. כבר מפורש על ידי שלמה, kvar
meforash al yedei shlomo, no, we see from שלמה shlomo שנאמר לשמוע
אל הרינה ואל התפלה, shenne'emar lishmoa el harina ve'el hatefillah,
to hear the רינה, rina, the rejoicing and the prayer. רינה זו
תפלה, rina zu tefillah, תפלה זו בקשה. tefillah zu bakashah.
רינה rina is prayer, meaning is the sort of שבח. shevach. תפלה
tefillah is the בקשה bakashah part. So it's quite fascinating that on
the one hand, it implicitly is labeling תפלה tefillah as the שבח,
shevach, not the בקשה, bakashah, but then immediately afterwards it's saying the
word תפלה tefillah in the פסוק pasuk means the בקשה bakashah part.
Okay. אין אומר דבר אחר אמת ויציב אבל אחר התפלה. ein omer
davar achar emet veyatziv aval achar hatefillah. So
before you do אמת ויציב emet veyatziv leading into the שמונה עשרה,
shmoneh esrei you don't interrupt. And now we're getting not just sort
of broad strokes about a direction, we're getting very practical about the
text. After אמת ויציב, emet veyatziv, you don't interrupt. גאולה geulah has
to lead in. But after, at the end of the דאוונינג, davening,
אפילו כסדר וידוי של יום הכפורים אומר. afilu keseder vidui shel yom
hakippurim omer. You can say as long as you want, even as
long as the וידוי vidui of יום כיפור, yom kippur, which again
seems to be emphasizing like why would I have thought in the
middle of this discussion I'm going to insert something after אמת ויציב?
emet veyatziv? And again, because this whole thing is not, is about
this personal experience of prayer, and it's giving broad strokes, so you
might think personalize it as much as you want. No, no, no,
there are some limits.
גאולה לתפילה. geulah litfillah. If you want to give your own text,
you can do it at the end of שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei
Right. Just to add to what you
were just saying, this part deals with, you know, how do you
actually do it. We've already dealt with the theoretical underpinnings of how
the structure is and so on, but now when we come to
how you actually do it, you have to look at some other
sources, how other people did it, where other people did it.
Right,
so we're not just talking here about guidelines and rules, we're talking
about like starting to sort of see them as models about how
we should sort of approach.
Once we've established the theoretical structural things, it's not really relevant to
the question of this פרק, how do you actually דאוון. daven. Right,
right.
Okay, so let's just now finish this point off, and then we'll
continue with חנה chana when we return. So the גמרא says, איתמר
נמי, itmar nami, it's also taught, אמר רב יצחק בר אשי אמר
רב, amar rav yitzchak bar ashi amar rav, אף ישאל אדם צרכיו
בשומע תפלה, af yishal adam tzerakhav beshome'a tefillah, and here you are
saying you can even add your personal prayer in the, not only
after the שמונה עשרה, shmoneh esrei but in the text of the
שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei itself. שומע תפלה shome'a tefillah is an open
opportunity to fit, to put in your personal text. אם בא לומר
אחר תפלתו אפילו כסדר וידוי של יום הכפורים אומר. im ba lomar
achar tfillato afilu keseder vidui shel yom hakippurim omer. There are different
degrees in which that balance is struck. If you want to do
it in the שמונה עשרה in שומע תפלה, shome'a tefillah, you can
make like short insertions. If you want to go out to town,
do it after שמונה עשרה before you maybe you step back, before
your עוקר רגליו, oker raglav, but do it after שמונה עשרה and
this is again playing with that balance of the structure and of
the personal. We will continue after דאוונינג davening with the model of
חנה. chana.